Guide to the Pierrepont family papers ARC.263
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Series 5: Rail Lines in Brooklyn, 1868-1898; 0.1 Linear Feet
  This series contains material relating to the proposed development of various rail lines in Brooklyn, primarily in Brooklyn Heights along Montague Street. The series documents the Pierreponts's objections to railway development impacting their property and business, and their negotiations permitting development. The series includes correspondence, legal agreements, legal advice, judicial reports, circulars, clippings, and petitions. Principal matters concern the Nassau Cable Railway Company of Brooklyn and the Covered Tube Cable Railway Company. Also included is Henry Pierrepont, Jr's correspondence to Governor Cornell opposing an elevated railroad on Furman Street.
  - Nassau Cable Railway Company of Brooklyn: Proposed Montague St. and Atlantic Ave. Railroads, 1868, 1883-1885 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Covered Tube Railway Co. and Brooklyn Heights Railroad Co.: Proposed Montague St. Railroad, 1886-1898 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1880-1890 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Furman Street Elevated Railroad, 1877, 1880 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Series 6: Brooklyn Waterfront and Ferries, 1816-1890; 1.1 Linear Feet
  The series opens with manuscript material related principally to the Union Ferry Company, followed by material related more specifically to Pierrepont property. This is followed by 2 folders of material related to Henry Pierrepont's history of the ferries and by printed matter.
  This series provides rich documentation concerning the development of the Brooklyn waterfront and East River ferry service, especially with regard to the Union Ferry Company during the mid-nineteenth century. The series includes correspondence, legal agreements, leases, corporate formation documents, and court filings. In addition to substantial manuscript material, there is printed material, such as New York Supreme Court decisions, government committee reports, leases, and pamphlets. Much of the material concerns negotiations with New York City and Brooklyn municipal authorities over franchise and property rights. Overall, strategic business objectives are a focus of the series, rather than day-to-day operational or financial matters. Nonetheless, there is material on specific matters, including the 1852 strike of ferry pilots and the 1883 experiment to replace gas lighting with electric on a ferry. The Fulton Ferry, South Ferry and Hamilton Avenue Ferry are well represented in the series, along with reference to Manhattan locations, such as the Wall Street Ferry. The Atlantic Dock Company and Williamsburgh Ferry Company are also represented.
  The series also includes an incomplete handwritten manuscript of Henry E. Pierrepont's Historical Sketch of the Fulton Ferry and its Associated Ferries, along with correspondence, notes and other materials compiled in connection with the history. The series includes maps, sketches, correspondence, legal agreements, and other documents concerning the bulkhead, docks, piers, and other structures on Pierreponts's waterfront property (also see Series 3 for maps and other related material).
  - Union Ferry Company (5 folders), 1837-1890 (Box 4, Folder 5-9)
  - Union Ferry Company: Pilot's Strike, 1852 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Union Ferry Company: Electric Lights, 1883 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    Includes electric company proposals (e.g., United States Illuminating Company, Edison Electric Illuminating Company of N.Y), correspondence, and cost benefit figures related to Union Ferry Company's experiment with electricity as a replacement for gas lighting.
  - Pierrepont Waterfront Property (3 folders), 1816-1871 (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
    Includes tracings of Fulton Ferry Landing as surveyed by Thomas Poppleton, 1816.
  - Brooklyn Ferry History (2 folders), 1877-1882 (Box 5, Folder 4, 5)
  - Print material (4 items), 1820s, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Print material (7 items), 1838-1839 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Print material (8 items, incl. 1 manuscript), 1845-1849 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Print material (28 items in 4 folders), 1850-1857 (Box 5, Folder 9-12)
  - Print material (7 items), 1860-1861, 1867 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Print material (6 items), 1876-1878, 1884 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Series 7: Newspaper Clippings, 1832-1915; 1.33 Linear Feet
  The loose clippings are arranged in rough subject and chronological order.
  The series is comprised of many loose clippings and one scrapbook. The scrapbook is Civil War themed and includes clippings concerning battles, naval ships and other weaponry, military maneuvers, political developments, cartoons, and individuals. The scrapbook also holds some ephemera. The loose clippings are principally from the mid-nineteenth century and concern Brooklyn ferries, docks and waterfront. There are also some clippings concerning the Pierreponts, including information about their property, biography, obituaries, and Henry's opposition to the consolidation of Brooklyn and New York City. Newspapers represented include, from Brooklyn, the Daily Advertiser, Daily Eagle, Daily Freeman, Daily Union, Evening Star, and Long Island Star, and from New York, the Dispatch, Enquirer, Herald, Times, and World.
  - Loose Clippings (19 folders), 1832-1915 (Box 6, Folder 4-22)
  - Civil War Scrapbook, 1860s (Box 90, Folder 1)
- Series 8: Diaries, 1797-1888; 0.42 Linear Feet
  Henry Evelyn Pierrepont's diaries are presented first, in chronological order. Miscellaneous material found with a diary is foldered with the diary or in a separate folder immediately following. The final two folders hold the transcribed excerpts from the Hezekiah Beers Pierrepont diaries.
  The bulk of the series includes the diaries Henry Evelyn Pierrepont (senior) maintained for the last decade of his life, from 1877 until March 19, 1888, nine days prior to his death. The numbering of the diaries, and an 1855 fragment, suggest that Pierrepont maintained a diary for many decades, but these are not in the collection and are not known to be extant. Each diary covers one calendar year and is numbered consecutively. The entries are handwritten and each diary begins with a one-page timeline of the year's major events.
  Daily entries typically include notes on the weather, Pierrepont's activities for the day, and other events of significance to Pierrepont. Though most are brief factual statements, Pierrepont expresses personal opinions about many matters. The daily entries are generally brief and concern the range of Pierrepont's interests: family, finances, commercial activities, civic activities, and politics. Personal notes include such matters as reflections on family deaths and lists of New Year's Day callers on Pierrepont and Pierrepont's calls on others. Pierrepont includes observations on local events, such as the blizzard of March 1888, and on some national events, such as his concern about communism in response to railroad labor strife in the summer of 1877. The diaries include descriptions of his travel, including at least one trip to Europe, in 1878. The series includes a separate log of his travels over four decades.
  Miscellaneous documents found in the diaries remain in the series. Among these is an acknowledgement of payment signed by G. Stuart for portraits for William Constable (1797), a letter from Pierrepont to State Senator Kirnan requesting his support in defeating a bill (1884), and an almanac page with information about the Brooklyn Bridge (1884).
  Also in the series are typescript transcriptions of extracts from diaries of Hezekiah Beers Pierpont and biographical notes.
  - Henry E: Diaries (14 folders), 1877-1888 (Box 7, Folder 1-14)
  - Henry E: Diary Summary, 1855 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Henry E: Travel Log, 1843-1885 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Hezekiah B: Diary Extracts and Historical Notes (2 folders), 1806-1820 (Box 7, Folder 17, 18)